[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host jeff doolittle it's my
pleasure to invite davide bedin as our
guest on the show today for an
exploration of dapper the distributed
application runtime
david dean is a cloud native
architecture enthusiast with strong and
relevant experience with cloud platforms
as a cloud solution architect at
microsoft davide is responsible for the
guidance and support of enterprise
customers in embracing the cloud
paradigm a key enabler of their digital
transformation
his recently published book practical
microservices with dapper and net
help software teams rapidly build cloud
native microservices by reducing or
eliminating much of the boilerplate and
plumbing which are typically involved in
building such solutions
davide welcome to software engineering
radio hi jeff thank you very much for
inviting me really excited to have this
chance to talk about dapper great well
speaking of what is dapper and why
should our listeners care about it yeah
so dapper is the acronym for distributed
application runtime
it's a project that
originates from microsoft probably a
couple of years ago so yes
we are celebrating these days the second
anniversary
and so i started
getting interested about dapper since
the very beginning so
even a small disclaimer i not involved
in the development of dapper and not
part of the product group i really
consider myself as a
professional enthusiast of dapper
and so pretty much since the beginning
combining
my experience as a developer and an
independent software vendor before
joining microsoft and
also the experience i see with my
customers i immediately feel compelled
to learn more about dapper
so
as a distributed application runtime and
the runtime from my perspective is one
of the most relevant
letter in the in the upper acronym
because it differentiated from framework
so
when you start to think about
distributed application multiple
components which
have the need
to communicate operate
in a
varied
environment
you will soon face
the need to have
dependencies
to frameworks in order to do
any of the
building blocks any of the operation you
are used to whether it's managing state
having invocation between one component
and the other and so this is
the area in which uh dapper and
the distributed application runtime
aims to bring benefit
to the users so when we begin
distributing there's unique challenges
and it sounds like what you're saying is
dapper is specifically meant to help
address the challenges of moving from
components that say run all together in
memory with the same language and the
same runtime and now what we're doing is
we're saying we're going to have a
runtime that's going to allow us
to handle a lot of those challenges of
distributing components that are often
left to maybe framework dependencies or
maybe language specific dependencies and
maybe be able to detach ourselves from
those dependencies
yeah yeah so
this is really one of the objective of
darpr
is to
give you the ability to choose freely
based on your architecture
your style
uh your languages and also the
frameworks
whether you want to split your
distributed application in many or fewer
components
because it will remove as a runtime
it will remove
what i
would
consider attacks
on the need for your component to
sustain over time a set of dependencies
so
we can start for example with the
ability of one component to communicate
with another component
which dapper provides a building block
for
named service to service invocation
so
if you have the same language
in both components
which has been my past experience while
this might not be that complex
but in reality is much more complex
because as you said there are different
languages
and each language might have a different
framework
and these frameworks will have a
different roadmap and they will probably
not move in sync
in order to
support
that mechanism remote the procedure call
or multi-location
framework in one language and the other
so it will get complicated
yeah and that's kind of the tip of the
iceberg isn't it i mean as soon as
you're going and you know as soon as
you're communicating over something
other than direct memory or maybe in you
know a socket or something like that now
you're gonna have other issues like what
about security what about reliability
and retry i could go on and on right but
i'm imagining these are the kinds of of
problems that dapper is addressing which
have been addressed but to your point
it's addressing them in a way that
allows
a breadth of access because different
languages in different teams who maybe
would have had trouble integrating
before
it sounds like dapper's intending to
lower that bar to those different
approaches and teams integrating their
components together is that correct yeah
yeah absolutely so in a sense
dapper is not only a language agnostic
approach
to building microservices because in the
end and these days most of us are
building architecture
with microservices it's also enabling
future languages that has have not been
invented so far to support because it
brings the barrier of entry as low as an
http
api or jrpc api too but
the overall point of topper is that it
is a runtime
that using the sidecar pattern
lives side by side with your application
so
if i'm starting to use damper in my
local
development machine my sidecar will be
another process
but when we speak about microservices
probably we are and this is the the
destination i'm moving forward
we are speaking about container
orchestrator or something like
kubernetes
so
in that
environment your side car will be
another container leaving side by side
in the same pot with your application
so the http api will be
available to you
in a very simple consistent way using
standards wherever they are already
available or established
and instead of frameworks dependencies
in your code
you will interact and you will be
invoked by
a sidecar working side by side with your
application
okay
so let's make sure for listeners who
aren't familiar with the sidecar pattern
i think maybe there was a little bit of
description there of what it is but
maybe more explicitly what exactly is
the sidecar pattern because that's
broader than just dapper so that's some
that's a pattern dapper's adopting so
maybe give us a brief overview on what
the sidecar pattern is
yeah so when you think about
let's say even locally on you on a
single box
you can have a piece of code
working inside of your process
okay and this happens when you load off
a library from a framework
and
so that code will execute inside of your
environment so
you share some of the dependencies with
that framework you are running let's say
your language of choice is python
probably you're using
frameworks built in python and probably
you have to get to a certain alignment
on the versions
so
something that you can do with sidecar
is to split
the overall application
your code for example from
whether it's a common function a common
feature that you want to provide to all
of your application or rely on another
component a third-party component
and you make it run on another process
separate from yours
and so
in this situation you have many
advantages
one is that
the resources in your processes are only
used by your
your code your application
and that anything that happens in the
two the two side cards your application
and the one that you are using does not
influence the other
but it's more about the separation of
responsibility and expectations
so the way to be able to interact
between one side car and other
could be various double
choose to implement
locally reachable
api
so
going back to the example of
running locally in your
development machine you know that the
localhost
the default port which is 3500
you will reach
the dapper sidecar
process
for that
you have instantiated for your
application
and pretty much the same with certain
level of change will happen
if instead of your local machine you are
running into a into a pod
in
kubernetes cluster
so the service that i'm dependent on
i'm really dependent on this middle
piece this sidecar that stands in the
middle between me and the other service
that i'm dependent on and then decisions
about whether i'm accessing that locally
or remotely are encapsulated within how
i configure that sidecar
yeah yeah that's pretty much the concept
and the goal
with
dapper is that
if your distributed application has
let's say two components
each component will have its own cider
car
so
if i have component a that
it's written in net
and component b is written in node
they will both communicate
with their own science car
so let's say i'm in local
my local environment
i'm going to have each of my application
if
my component will have its own sidecar
if i'm running on kubernetes component a
and component b will be separate
thoughts
because this way i will for example be
able to scale it independently okay so
what we were used to do with yams we
probably placed component b
on a different
kind of
maybe more or less resources
and maybe we scale this way in the in
the very old days
with container orchestrator or engine
like
kubernetes you accomplish pretty much
the same goal
having multiple
parts of the same component running and
dealing with all the requests
so this is pretty much how dapper relies
on the sidecar
pattern in order to give you
the ability to
interact with any other application
regardless of their language regardless
where they are located
could they be in the same
node where your application is located
could it be in another node and
most of the time
it will be on a separate note
it will not influence the way your right
application
because you will still have
decided car at your disposal that you
can reach with an http api so every
language
is able to use to interact with an http
api
right right
so it's something i said before on the
show and i say it a lot for people who
know me personally too
the two hardest problems in computer
engineering
are information hiding and dependency
management
and really to say dependency management
in a way is to say information hiding
which i could get into another time but
you've mentioned dependency management
and things already and i think it's
relevant here too that if i'm using this
sidecar
i'm able to hide a lot of information
about what's happening behind the
sidecar on the other side of any
components or services that i need to be
able to interact with
and that isn't to say i don't worry
about them obviously as soon as you
distribute you're going to have to deal
with latency and retry and things you
wouldn't necessarily have to locally but
you can make those decisions in how you
configure the sidecars and now it sounds
like dappers trying to address those
major issues information hiding and
dependency management yeah absolutely
and
so far i mentioned this service to
service invocation which is a building
block one of the seven building blocks
of dapper
but the value in what you are describing
is more evident when you switch to
state management
and the publishing subscribe
which are two building blocks because
with state management well we could
probably have a
one hour talk on just state management
but to keep it very
simple and short
let's say your component has the need to
keep some state aside
so your code can be simpler
because it will be
stateless
service
and your state will be handled by
someone else so you're shifting
one of the
difficult responsibility
we tend to have in distributed
application
which is to keep state between different
calls from
the same client
so
with state management the responsibility
will pass to the double sided car but
then starts probably
the value in the extensibility of topper
so
dapper comes out with
probably then more than 70 components
already available another coming up
being built by the community
in order to
store this state
in different services
whether it's redis cash
whether it's couchdb
or a cloud vendor
operated database as a service
so
dapper does not only have the aim to be
language agnostic but to be platform
agnostic and
we mentioned kubernetes
we mentioned
local environment which are the two
deployment options but it's also a cloud
vendor agnostic so if you go to the
documentation of the upper you will see
that for state management but also for
publish and subscribe
you will have support for
many of the services provided not only
by asia but also by the other cloud
vendors
okay
so you mentioned building blocks and i
get the sense that that's a pretty
important element here and you said
there's seven we don't need to list the
seven necessarily but
previously to the show you mentioned
that there were a few core building
blocks and so state management is
clearly one of them as you just
mentioned
and is there anything else on state
management that's worth mentioning
before we maybe dive into a few of the
other core building blocks oh yeah
absolutely so the concept here is that
you code your component
counting on the availability of the api
by dapper on the sidecar
so you can interact directly you can use
an sdk for
pretty much any of the language
available today and present in the
market
but the choice on
whether you're placing the state
on
an azure cosmos db
or
as you are local
you're landing in it locally on redis
this does not sit into your code
or your code configuration
it's a component defined in yaml format
which is pretty
common to everyone that has to deal
with kubernetes
and i mean not that did they want to
deal with kubernetes but they have to
deal with it
yeah so
it's something that will be decided
whether by you whether by the operation
team
you will be able via configuration of
components of the upper components to
switch your application from
running local to running natively on
azure with by just
changing a component configuration
and this applies to all the other big
blocks
so the next one probably
publish and subscribe i think
service to service state and publish
subscribe are probably the one that you
use
the most time
okay so service to service
basically meaning i have one service i
know what service i want to call and now
i'm going to call
that other service
now imagine the the sidecar
is going to help me with dealing with
the location of that service so that i'm
not coupled to that as the caller but
the interface of that service is what i
can depend on is that a fair assessment
yeah so
dapper does not intervene in the
definition of the payload you are going
to pass to the other component because
it has an opinion on how to build a
distributed application
whether with microservices
architecture but it leads
to
your language your choices your
framework
how to deal with the payload
what you have to specify with service
invocation is
the name of the other component in the
adapter ecosystem
and then the method you are going to
call to the other side
and so your request from your sidecar
will go through
the environment
on kubernetes it will use the kubernetes
mechanism to find the corresponding
services which you will not have to care
anymore about and will pass the payload
to the method you specified
so
between europe component
and sidecar on both ends
it can be http to keep it simple very
easily readable
you can also use jrpc if you
have the need
but the great thing is that
between the sidecar of the upper
which as i said can be distributed over
many different nodes communication will
happen in grpc
and will be
secure with mtls so you get
many benefits by default
by just interacting with a simple http
api
you just mentioned a new one there too
which i think is important to highlight
you mentioned mtls which is mutual
transport layer security and so i
believe that's the correct and we'll put
a link to that in the show notes in case
i'm wrong and even if i'm right you
still might want to look that up
so i'm also getting
i want to say quote for free nothing's
free but i mean to me i'm not having to
implement now transport layer security
between my components dapper is giving
me giving that to me yeah yeah in
kubernetes there are a number of dapper
system components
one of these has the responsibility to
give the ability to any upper side car
to establish
mutual secure channel of communication
between each other
and so yes you get mtls
as a feature
of dapper
and then once you have control sort of
of that pipeline of communication
between
two components and since now you have
this run time and these side cars
between each side
you can pretty much
manage that pipeline by
adding whatever i mean it feels a lot
like middleware with a mediator pattern
sort of like if you're you know doing
you know spring apps or you're doing
applications with asp.net core you can
inject middleware into your pipeline and
do pretty much whatever you want at that
point it just sounds like that brought
to more of the service to service you
know application application level
yeah yeah yeah absolutely in a sense
it's really as you described and
something i recently experienced
so i had the chance to have a
hackfest as we call
with a customer about dapper
and it has been mainly run on
another language that i'm not familiar
with
so i was a bit worried that you know
being a.net developer or what in the
past at least
my focus is always looking at you know
the sdk what the sdk provides
and so
my worry was
but what if
the
corresponding sdk
for the other language
does not match the libraries the
frameworks
that the customer is was using
and not for this preference or using
this sdk or not with dapper but as an
experiment we chose to run the hackfest
by interacting directly with the http
api
of dapper and so this customer had
their language their framework
which
was used to pass
a lot of
data
inside the payload or as headers and
we really did not have to touch
anything because as i said previously
the upper doesn't mandate what
you put in the payload and in the
headers you pass
and so it has been
kind of eye-opening for me that i
consider i spend a lot on dapper
to see how easy is to
well i don't want to downplay with easy
but how efficient it is
to
insert dapper into an existing framework
that
might do things in a way that is
different
for me for example to what asp.net does
with you know odd
the attributes
and the asp.net framework
right so you were able now to integrate
with
services components written by this
other team without having to first
understand their language their
framework their development tools
everything about their build chains and
pipelines and everything instead you
were able to consume it and interact
with it using dapper and then vice versa
you'd be able to deliver something to
them in the other direction as well
so that sounds really powerful
and
yeah so taking that now and moving to
the next building block you mentioned
before which is publish and subscribe
which you know basically is one service
is sending out a message and it doesn't
necessarily know it really shouldn't
know who's listening but other services
can subscribe to those messages and
receive them so
talk a bit about that and how
dapper implements publish subscribe in a
way that's maybe
different or an improvement on typical
approaches
oh yeah yeah and
so with the publish and subscribe as the
goal of dapper is to offer a consistent
set of apis
from the api perspective it doesn't
change a lot
so
instead of invoking your publishing a
payload
but this is one of the building blocks
in which i speak from my
personal point of view
it gives a lot of sense to observe your
existing approach
to the publish and subscribe and maybe
think about if
even
inserting dapper
and substituting the way that you deal
with sending and receiving messages
with dapper
means gives you value i think it will
really
give you a lot of value and a lot of
help because it will transform the way
your
components your microservices
are listening to events
to a complete event-driven approach
because
so i spent a lot of time with azure
service bus and other
technologies
and so each one has its own way of
dealing with the
consuming of messaging
whether it's by looking it
at the content and then deciding
whether to process or consuming directly
by reading you know
each one has its own
approaches
sure and example like rabbitmq or sqs
right they're all unique in some ways in
response absolutely absolutely also
because they have different history
different use cases from which they
originated and grew so
all great reason to
be different
but if you are creating a new greenfield
distributed application or you are you
want to innovate on an exiting one
the fact that
there is a cider car side by side
with your component
that is
being configured to use
on azure let's say azure service bus
and maybe a rabbit mq if you are working
locally or you have an on-premise
installation of your solution
and counting that is the it will be the
cycle responsibility to
properly use in the best possible way
the
libraries
for consuming these services and you
will not have
a different approach in your code
to
react to messages
coming from service bus or rabbit mq it
will be the same
because your approach will be having
driven because in fact the side car will
will ask your components
first if you are interested
into subscribing to
any topic that is exchanged in the
messaging in the publish and subscribe
building blog
and it will ask for the endpoint that
the sidecar has to call to inform you
that the new message or event
has been received so you will simplify a
lot
this is really helpful from my
experience and the perspective i have
during these days working with customers
yeah and something you said i really
appreciate it as well and it's coming
before you've mentioned development
locally versus you know directly against
cloud resources and assets and i'm a
huge fan as much as possible and i push
it pretty far if possible to do
development entirely locally because
when the internet goes down or github
goes down or whatever else goes down
especially if you need oh i can't get to
sqs because my aws cluster is this or
that or my kubernetes cluster is once
again you know on the fritz it's like
well hold on i can do everything locally
and that ability you just described you
know i'm not going to run a full uh you
know sqs instance locally although i'm
aware that there's solutions for that
and it escapes my mind right now but
there is a project that that's a
stand-in for a lot of those amazon cloud
services and i'll find and put in the
show notes but i can also take a
different tack which is i can run rabbit
mq locally but i can be confident that
i'm going to get the same behavior out
of azure service bus when i switch over
to the cloud there's a ton of power in
that
how is dapper doing that behind the
scenes how in the world can it you know
manage this it must be doing some sort
of
magic or using some other existing
tooling to pull this off
nothing magic so dapper well i think
it's really i sometimes also think about
well
this can be true how easy it will it is
but usually it pivots very fast on
why i didn't had it
before in my life
but that's this is a completely
different story
and so dapper is an open source project
and is written entirely in go
okay
so it relies on the
components for each of these
technologies the 70 more
components available by using the
corresponding
go library for
each of the service so
you have right now
a large community that is using the same
software you are using
from different perspective
so and
knowing that your
client library client to the
messaging subsystem the messaging system
of choice
that is being used
on different setup different scale
different languages but it's the very
same
library well you have probably more
cases
than the average
on that
gives you the trust that
someone else will
see the way to to improve it and to
update the component
or if you have a compelling need
you will choose that it can be you
as an individual
as a
component a customer to become a
contributor to improve
that component
for the benefit of the overall community
sure but what about
actually running this stuff i mean i
imagine i need to download some things
to get started and then i say okay well
i locally i want to run these things
with with these versions of say
messaging or state management but then
in the cloud i want it to be these
things
what's happening locally in order to
enable this all to happen is staffer
doing everything itself or is it relying
on something else
yeah so the configuration happens
via configuration files
so
this they will influence
which of the
many components for each of the building
blocks
you will choose to use and
from that point you will have the
ability to influence
the way
each
component works by injecting
specific configuration so
with service bus you have the option to
configure
some settings that might be different in
rabbit and q but this difference
will stay in the component
definition
right based on whether it's local or
cloud yeah absolutely or
yeah the configuration do i have to
install all of these dependent services
myself locally it's something that will
happens during the initialization
of dapper so whether it's local you run
the upper init
once you install the command line
interface or if you are in a kubernetes
environment you can do the same or you
can use
a different approach which is unheld
chart
and you specify which version of dapper
you want to run and this
will
place the system components
and the code
that will be used
by the possible configuration
of your components
so it will be decided in a sense that
will carry
the options for let's say
use a rapid mq use azure service pass
for the publisher subscribe or use this
or other database for the state
management
okay you mentioned something before i
want to make sure that doesn't just fly
by you said the words dapper init so
dapr space init
which refers to the dapper command line
yeah so
yeah maybe speak to that a little bit
absolutely so the damper command line
interface
is a tool that you can install on
any box
that helps you
with the development experience so
locally you will use dapper
to run an application with dapper run
and you will specify the name of the
application and the other settings
you will not use dapper run
once you run your application in
kubernetes because
in that part it will be someone else's
responsibility to
start
your pod with the container of your
image
on kubernetes
it's
as simple as injecting
some dapper specific annotations
into your deployment yaml file
because yaml gets everywhere
and so if you have your application and
you
have been able to put it into a
container
and
you want to run it on kubernetes it's
highly likely that you already have
an existing yaml file describing
how your application is going to start
which part does it use etc
but what you just need to do is to
inject
some double annotation in this file
and there will be
no other requirements
other than this
in order to let dapper know
that
your container has the interest
to interoperate with damper and so
dapper will inject the side car
into your
port automatically without
you as the developer to deal with all
these configurations
so you mentioned container again and i
think
that's pointing to let's say i want to
install the dapper command line
interface which i can go find probably
just you know do a web search for dapr
space cli and and you mentioned i can
pretty much run that anywhere
if it's using containers then i imagine
i'm also going to need to take a
dependency on some engine for
running containers locally
yeah yeah so locally
well not necessarily because locally by
default
dapper installs the
the radius just in order to give you a
very easy and fast chance to
run
hello world a very simple
application locally and also does
install locally one of the components
of the system components of the upper
which is the placement service which is
necessary
for the for another building block which
is the actors
but you have the ability to install
dapper also
without this component
and so
locally
it
for example what i in my book
what i instruct or
teach the reader to do is to use the
upper run to
run the
net solution the dotnet projects
directly in the avs code environment so
in that stage
while i'm in the development
phase
i'm not already putting all of my
code
in a container deployment option
i'm just
telling dapper
to run side by side with my
my.net application so in that part there
are no
containers involved
container
are a very good way to deploy an
application to
so
from that point you will have to deal
with with containers but
if kubernetes is
one
appealing compute option for your
application
you already approach the
good
and the complexities of putting your
application into a container
okay
yeah that's great and back to something
you said before those three services
that you're going to automatically get
when you dapper in it and dapper run so
you're going to get redis
immediately for state management and for
pub sub
now of course keeping in mind this is
if you need persistence you might need
to reconsider but at least for getting
started you're building application code
and so now all of that infrastructure
you can sort of say i'll get to that
later first i want to get my application
code working
and then we'll get to the the actor
building block later but basically now i
have these three services running
that are giving me access to these
dapper building blocks with no
additional
configuration or work on my part i can
just start writing
application code
it's really just default configuration
that you have on your local machine
so once you run upper init by default
you will have to yaml configuration file
that you uh
that have been provided by dapper that
points to
the local
this
container so if you install the upper
init
you will get just as a starting point
redis but is
there is not a requirement to use redis
even locally
because as we speak
also because it's my experience
i tend to consider
the local experience the development
experience
so
i heavily rely on redis just to test
if i'm able to run my components if
everything is fine i use it as a test
but there might be situations in which
you run upper even locally even on the
ends
but you will not rely already so you
will rely on rabbit mq and maybe
a couch whatever
other local database option you have
with
persistence obviously
it's really just a way to ease the
experience of the developer
just after you run the period
okay so we have those core building
blocks service to service state
management publish and subscribe
and then i think where we start to get
to another level of power is is the
building blocks called bindings and in
my research for our interview today
it kind of occurred to me that in many
respects dappers enabling what's you
know been called the hexagonal
architecture pattern which i'll put a
link to in the show notes which
basically it boils down to ports and
adapters and so you're back to
information hiding and dependency
management you know the canonical
old-school interior application was the
database is sort of at the bottom layer
and then everything you know stacks up
above that but you end up getting this
nefarious coupling because the data
accessory gets called the database your
business layer gets coupled with data
logic your front end gets coupled to the
business logic and you really haven't
solved anything you've just made a
distributed mess now instead of a
monolithic mess
and so now what we're saying is flip
that around the database is outside our
you know your hexagon if you will or
it's something you bind to as we'll
discuss here or whatever these other
things are right you have ports into
your system you have adapters out of
your system
so
talk a little bit about bindings and how
they can kind of help us with that
notion of instead of
having these dependencies leak up
through our systems instead we put them
outside so that we depend on them in a
decoupled fashion
yeah absolutely so if we consider the
other building blocks for comparison so
with service to service invocation you
gain the ability to
establish direct communication between
two components
one knows the existence of the other
with publish and subscribe you are still
establishing a relationship with two
applications what changes is that
the subscriber
is probably unaware of the existence of
the publisher it just knows that
having expressed interest for a message
for an event depending on what you
consider
he will receive it and with the seventh
driven approach it will react to the
information
and so these are two ways to have your
components
in your dapper application to work
together
what i consider the bindings the input
and output binding is a way to
extend your application to the outside
world
to something that is already there
like
enterprise
event streaming platform that has been
around for
for longer than your application
and it will stay a long time there
and you want as your application is
getting built you want to consume
events that come from that source of
information
and so the messages that you will
receive
they are sent in in a generic way there
is nothing specific about dapper in the
way that you will find the
messages streaming in kafka
stream or in
in azure in azure event hub
you will configure an input binding
in a similar fashion to what you do with
publish and subscribe
but
it's meant to be a way to reach to
outside of your application integrate
with an existing flow of information so
because what i forgot to mention is
what gives you
the upper for example in the publish and
subscribe
is that it by using cloud events
it enables
full end-to-end visibility
for
observability which is another building
block
because it inserts metadata
so
whether your
application internally between
components at one time is using service
to service or they're using publish and
subscribe
the way that
they will share traces
via observability and by leveraging
another existing standard which is open
telemetry they will look pretty much the
same in reality it will be a different
approach but they will look
at component a and component b
interacting at different times in
different ways once you consume a kafka
stream from
another system
you will consume messages as they are
and if you want to give back to the
messaging
platform the enterprise service bus or
whatever you want to name it
you will send raw payload
without
enriching them
with anything that is
not dapper specific but
is uh more closer to your application
so and streaming on event is just an
example you know
consuming events from twitter
which is one of the
first example you find when you go to
dapper dot io or talks about the upper
because it tells the story of bindings
but you know it's just
an external system
that is not necessarily part of your
application
it's another application or something
really outside of even your enterprise
your company
and you want to find a similar way with
component configuration
to consume events from it and react to
events from it
yeah and you mentioned something
important i want to make sure we
highlight which is you mentioned cloud
events and that is a really important
thing to mention because cloud events is
part of the cloud native computing
foundation
the short form is the cncf which we'll
put a link to all of those things in the
show notes and am i correct in saying
that dapper is also part of the cloud
native computing foundation
so what i
know is that the process of
integrating automating
the project has been started it's a
public process
i'm not familiar with the current status
but if you look go to the
upper roadmap which is publicly
available and on github you will
see the
the current state of the affair okay so
it's incubated as a cncf project that
was what i recalled but it isn't
necessarily in it yet
but that is that process is going and as
you mentioned it is open source but also
that embracing open standards i think is
kind of the deeper story there that
dapper isn't just reinventing the wheel
on a lot of these things it's adopting
what is there as existing standards as
well
yeah and this is one of the core
principles of the upper is to really use
standards wherever they are available
and have traction
in the community so we just mentioned
cloud events the other one is open
telemetry
and so instead of
inventing something new i think we all
agree
that is beneficial to everyone to
contribute
back to the success of an open standard
an open platform
by using it for example
and so this is open telemetry for
example is something and the
observability building block is
something that i would have really
treasured in my past
but really it was not around even the
concepts and so i had to build my own
stock
to have visibility of a request going
through many components
and sometimes i had to make choices on
whether it made sense to split one
larger component into two because
the roadmap
was diverging for one part of the
features
from another one so it was one
healthy discussion about
should they be two different components
or two different microservices
but
having
something more
one more component to handle to manage
to
bind to the
logging in stock i built my myself
you know it
influenced the discussion yeah it was a
limiting factor in a way that you didn't
really want that there's always going to
be limiting factors and constraints but
that's not the one you wanted and
so now we can take a different approach
before we you mentioned observability
before we move into that so
bindings you did mention things such as
other enterprise services or things that
are not dapper ready but i also want to
make sure we hit as well on
the other side of bindings which is
say for example connecting to databases
and maybe make a distinction between
when would you use state management
which we talked about before
versus when would you say use bindings
to a database instead of of state
management
yeah absolutely so
with state management dapper aims to
give you the ability to take the burden
of keeping a state
outside of your component so it your
code can be written
with a stateless approach and that's the
value of that component
and by doing this
it doesn't affect
your payload but it adds some
information
to the overall payload with just some
decoration but in a general sense it
will leave it as it is
but it's something specific to the state
and the api are as simple
as it's needed for a state management
it doesn't provide a full query for
query language so
you are meant to just keep the state
between calls and
nothing more than this you will still
have your database your line of business
sure and long-lasting uh database
right but the state management is more
like key value store it sounds like it's
that's it's just absolutely yeah as
opposed to
bindings maybe yeah now expand on that a
little bit for us what the distinction
would be there
yeah yeah and so with the inside with
bindings
you have the ability to interact with
another system
by just
sending and receiving a raw payload so i
don't remember which are currently the
database
supported as
both weather input and output binding i
suppose mostly as output bindings
by adapter
but yeah the sensor here is to
pass an information to
an external database without any
influence on what you are managing
so you mentioned observability is one of
those things you wished you had
and we i think a lot of us have been
there as soon as you choose to
distribute you find that the pain of the
lack of observability if you don't have
it
so
dapper obviously had this as a building
block and you mentioned before open
telemetry as well
so speak a little bit more to why
observability is so important in a
distributed application and how dapper
lowers the bar to getting observability
yeah so as you said
immediately as you create two components
as you split your application into
different pieces
you will have far more interactions
going through
less reliable communication channel than
being
inside the same process
so
you never account for false and retries
when
you or intermittent transient errors
when you interact with a library that
you load into your application but
as soon as you
go outside of your process and far more
relevant
as we are considering kubernetes as the
major compute option for microservice
oriented architecture you will cross
also the network boundary of ibm or
anode
in kubernetes terms and this will
increase
the
number of situation that
your application has to deal
so and this is just for service to
service communication
so when you start sending messages to
messaging system with the publish and
subscribe
it will happen at different times
on different nodes maybe
so
it will not even be in the same sequence
of events
so this is another complication
which will happen regardless
of the choice
you make on your framework your language
etc because they
they are part of the reality of running
a distributed application
and so
with observability building block and by
adopting the
open telemetry
you out of the box with just one
configuration which
you attach to your adapter application
you can specify
your application to
enable
the
forward of all the traces to a consumer
compatible log metrics consumer
compatible with the open telemetry stack
which will give you an end-to-end
visibility of
all the interaction that happened
regardless of the way that you are using
the developer api so if your components
just
leverage adapter for some of the
building blocks
let's say state manager maintenance
service to service these are the
this exchange between one damper
application the other and the
retrieval or update of an information
with the state
these are the
elements that will surface via open
telemetry
and that you can will be able to see
from any
viewer let's say any consuming
application
that can deal with that format that open
format
so
zipkin is one option application inside
can be another one
but also other tracing application
performance
monitoring
tracing and login platform can be used
so
it's highly likely that you will be able
to integrate it
your existing
platform with dapper because open
telemetry is a standard
so it's not
something magic
it's just that it's a standard and so
everyone
in the industry is embracing it
and so this is uh
an incredible value from the operational
side but it's also from the development
side because
you know that
you're
once you get an exception and there
there is a three cd
you as the developer and the operation
team will be able to see
the very same trace the very same
exchange
knowing where is taking too much time
how the code is flowing
so it's really
helpful
of development and optimization and
operational assets
yeah troubleshooting bugs but also
root cause analysis on outages or or
things of this nature
absolutely having that ability to do
distributed tracing is is important and
so that's great that dapper includes
that as a as a very important building
block
so i want to get started with dapper
let's say i have an existing application
and i don't want to have to do a bunch
of
rewriting redos
re-whatever like how can i get started
using this on an existing system
obviously for greenfield it sounds like
there's a lot of you know power here and
things i can do and that's great but you
know it's obviously it's always super
important to make sure that the new cool
things don't just leave everything in
the dust because we can't just rewrite
everything so
so how do we get started with dapper on
existing systems
yeah yeah absolutely so i don't know
what's your starting point but i tend to
look for
sdk wherever i i can but this just
because it's my background
but as i said
even for greenfield for a new
application sdk is
provided by dapper for all the language
is a starting point because it
accelerates the development
but one option is to use
dapper darkly via with the
http api and this is
the approach that you can take
to the price
which is a term that
is used in the upper eyes
yeah
that is using that upper community
which means to
to enable an existing application or
even a new
application to
interact with dapper via the api so yes
your application has
must have a way to
request
and send something to
an api
but it doesn't ask anything more
to the existing application
they it doesn't have to know about the
upper
and probably one of the first
scenario that you face on
uprising an application is
which is also very well documented into
the docs
dapper site
is
on
instructing an ingers controller
which is a component in kubernetes which
you use to
expose your internal your application
that is running internally
into the kubernetes cluster
you use it to expose it to
the outside world to to your customer to
your clients
okay and so
what developers had to do
was not only
to configure
to put their code into a container and
then configure a deployment
specification yaml but they also had to
deal with
you know services
from the kubernetes perspective how to
name to discover application how to name
application etc which is taken now
care by dapper
but by the uprising
you just inject
some annotations
into a deployment script so you can do
it
with nginx
as an example but any other ingers
controller
it applies the same and so
if your application has a way to
request
to reach
the resource via an http
and maybe do some translation
you will be able to use uh dapper
and it's something i
recently experienced
in a
scenario that we went through
we chose to take this approach of the
uprising an existing application
that
for sure already had
a place in which
it was possible to change the address
the url of the resource of the endpoint
and we changed it from the existing one
with a adapter specific
api endpoints pointing to the sidecar
and so
as nothing is mandated about the
parameters the adders the body
etc everything gets passed as you put it
so with an angus controller going back
to the
documented the well-documented sample
and something that i also went through
in my book
it's really easy given that you already
deal
with http api
right so if i have a one service
that is relying on another service and
let's say it's already communicating via
http
then
i can basically instead of having it
speak http to the existing endpoint i
can have it talk to the dapper sidecar
and then have dapper now
become the mediator between my service
and that other service and then i can
leverage all this other richness
like the observability that we mentioned
before and and everything else that
dapper can can provide so that's one way
to do it there's also a in my research i
found a project called dapper sidekick
which
sounds like it takes what you're
describing and it lowers the bar even
further are you familiar with that
project and maybe if you are explaining
a bit about what it does well i'm not
that familiar but it's something i
really remember from one of the
community calls which i attend as
many in the community
and so dapper has bi-weekly
community calls
we open for everyone so tapper also has
discord channels in which you can
talk
about all the components in addition to
the proper discussion on github but in
the community calls there are
many contributors like in this case
sidekick is a project started by man
group
in which they presented a new way
to leverage dapper or for deploying an
application
not obviously on the local machine as we
started our compensation not on
orchestrator like kubernetes but on
multiple vms
and so they extended the way
you can operate the damper inside the
car
in a way that enable them to rely on
dapper
for
the various building blocks
in a new scenario
which is
from my really from my external
perspective as uh
as someone that is closely looking and
loving the community and developer
project
is something expected absolutely but
nevertheless is amazing
and it's something.net specific if i
remember okay i think
maybe we can put in the
notes also the pointing to the
to the community course this specific
one in which they talked about service
because also the process
so so far i have been
successful in a way to build something
with dapper but
that example and many others
are relevant also to understand on
how can you build something new that did
not already exist with the upper support
new scenarios and contribute back
to the community which is something i
have not been able
yet to do
well except you did write a book
which is introducing people to the
technology yeah i'd say it is in a sense
that's a that's definitely a a
contribution to the community
have you ever really been happy with
your project management tool most are
too simple for a growing engineering
team to manage everything or too complex
for anyone to want to use them without
constant product shortcut formerly known
as clubhouse is different though because
it's worse wait no we mean it's better
shortcut is project management built
specifically for software teams it's
fast intuitive flexible powerful and
many other nice positive adjectives
let's look at some highlights team-based
workflows individual teams can use
shortcuts default workflows or customize
them to match the way they work org-wide
goals and roadmaps the work in these
workflows is automatically tied into
larger company goals it takes one click
to move from a roadmap to a team's work
to individual updates and vice versa
type vcs integrations whether you use
github git lab or bitbucket shortcut
ties directly to them so you can update
progress from the command line the rest
of shortcut is just as keyboard friendly
with their power bar allowing you to do
virtually anything without touching your
mouse throw that thing in the trash
iterations planning set weekly
priorities and then let shortcut run the
schedule for you with accompanying burn
down charts and other reporting give it
a try at shortcut.com sc radio again
that's shortcut.com se radio shortcut
again formerly known as clubhouse
because you shouldn't have to project
manage your project management
this has been a fascinating overview and
i'm sure listeners are aware that this
is really the tip of the tip of the
iceberg and if they want to dig deeper
into dapper i mean we didn't really have
time to get into two of the other
building blocks regarding secrets you
know you mentioned observability before
as something that you always wished you
had and and now you know i would say
secrets management is another one of
those that a lot of us are always
ripping our hair out about like why is
it so hard it's getting easier but but
still and then also the actor building
block is so powerful we could honestly
probably do a whole episode on actors
and how dapper enables actors but i
definitely want to encourage listeners
to check out davide's book you mentioned
the discord channel for dapper and there
are other books as well and there's the
community calls related to dapper for
those who want to get involved and just
a reminder this isn't a
microsoft or a.net thing although that's
sort of its genesis but dapper is
written and go the
building blocks are written and go
and there's lots of contributions from
lots of different communities which
really bears a lot of promise for the
the future we want to have which is
teams can use the tooling and toolings
and languages they're familiar with but
adopt standards for interoperation with
other services and that's it sounds like
a future i want to be a part of
absolutely and keep using the language
they
want they prefer they need
the frameworks they need
and also so be a language agnostic but
also be able to offer to
your customer to their customers an
application that can run
everywhere
because the world is getting more
complex the edge is playing more and
more important roles so
probably i tend to think as the
local environment as the development
environment
but the edge and asman group
demonstrated with the sidekick project
it can be even more rich
even outside of a kubernetes environment
absolutely well in the book there's also
some this github repository with code
examples and walkthroughs for listeners
as well but if listeners want to find
out what else you're up to where can
they go
yeah you can find me on twitter
and on linkedin my alias on twitter is
building davide
and same on linkedin and f2
and absolutely pick me if you
want to
know something more about dapper but i
encourage to go to the dot io
which is the starting point for dapper
and then
read the documentation on docs.you
and start from there
to learn more about this
rich new runtime well davide thank you
so much for joining me as a guest on
software engineering radio
thank you very much it has been a
pleasure thank you
this is jeff doolittle for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening